"Fasting for Cancer:
What About Cachexia?"
In 1974, an influential paper
was published decrying
physician-induced malnutrition as
the skeleton in the hospital closet ---
the fact that many patients in
hospitals were malnourished,
which the editorial board
of the journal of the AMA
described as shocking.
"Even a single case
is one too many,"
yet still to this day
the issue persists.
If anything, people with serious
illness would seem to need
even more nutrition,
not less, yet underfeeding
persists, involving as many as
50% of hospitalized patients.
The ethical principle of justice
requires that every patient
be fed enough, given
that hospital malnutrition
has been associated
with increased
risk of disease and death,
but is it cause and effect?
Does eating less
make you sicker,
or does being sicker
just make you eat less?
You don't know until
you put it to the test.
But would it be ethical to randomize
patients to remain starved?
I mean wouldn't nutritional
support obviously help?
It turns out, no. Not one,
but 22 randomized controlled
trials involving thousands
of malnourished patients
found that, sure,
you can plump them up;
however, there seemed to be
little effect on clinical outcomes.
In fact, sometimes it can
actually make things worse.
Maybe your body is losing
your appetite on purpose.
Ever since Hippocrates, fasting
has been offered as a treatment
for acute and chronic diseases,
based on the observation
that when people get sick, they
frequently lose their appetite,
so maybe that's part of our body's
wisdom and we shouldn't force it?
OK, but that was 2400 years ago.
What have we learned since?
Along with fever, decreased
food consumption is indeed
one of the most common signs
of infection, often regarded
as an undesirable
manifestation of sickness,
but it's actually an active,
beneficial defense mechanism.
Now obviously, chronic
under-nutrition can impair
our defenses, but data
suggest that in the short-term,
immune function can be enhanced
by lowering food intake.
Some of the data are crazy,
like 95% alive versus 95% dead
after the same infection,
but that was in mice
starved for 48 hours.
Obviously, you can't randomize
people to a fatal infection,
but what they showed is that
the blood from starved mice was
nearly 8 times better at
killing off the invading bacteria
in a petri dish.
It dramatically boosted
the capacity of their white blood
cells to kill off the pathogens.
Why can't we just test people
like that? Indeed, we can.
Researchers fasted
people for two weeks
on an 80 calorie a day diet,
and their white blood cells
showed the same kind of boost
in bacteria-killing activity,
a boost in antibody production,
and natural killer cell activity
increased by an average of 24%.
Now that's especially interesting
because our natural killer cells
don't just help clear infections,
but also kill cancer cells.
In fact, that's how they measured
natural killer cell activity by pitting
them against K562 cells --- those are
tumor cells, human leukemia cells.
So two weeks of fasting boosted
their bloodstream's ability
to kill off cancer cells by 24%.
So fasting is said to improve
anticancer immunosurveillance,
or more poetically
"stimulate the appetite of
the immune system for cancer. "
So why isn't fasting used more
to treat cancer? Until recently,
fasting therapy was not considered
to be a treatment option
in cancer, related to the fact that
a common therapeutic goal
in palliative cancer treatment
is to avoid weight loss
and to counteract the wasting
syndrome known as cachexia,
which is the ultimate cause
of death in many cancer cases.
Tumors are voracious,
rapidly expanding,
and needing lots of
energy and protein,
and so metabolically
reprograms our body
to start breaking down to feed it.
It does this by triggering
inflammation throughout the body.
It's not just that people
lose their appetite.
The fundamental difference
between weight loss
observed in cancer cachexia
and that seen in simple starvation
is the lack of reversibility
with feeding alone.
For example, here's the weight of
a cancer patient that started to drop.
No wonder: they were only taking
in a few hundred calories a day.
So in addition to giving them
about 100 grams of protein a day,
they stuck a tube into a vein and
infused up to 4,000 calories a day.
But it didn't matter.
They continued to lose weight.
Therapeutic nutritional
interventions to correct or reverse
cachexia have met
with little success.
The best treatment for
cancer cachexia therefore
is to treat the cause
and cure the cancer.
In fact, maybe forcing extra
nutrition on cancer patients
could be playing right
into the tumor's hands.
Like in pregnancy when the
fetus gets first dibs on nutrients
even at the mother's expense,
the tumor may be first
in the feeding line.
Maybe our loss of appetite
when we get cancer
is even a protective response.
But in the 1960s, TPN was born ---
total parenteral nutrition ---
where people no longer had to eat;
and you could infuse all the
nutrition people needed straight
into their veins, and the modern
era of nutrition support was born.
It became widely accepted
and implemented,
growing into a
multibillion-dollar industry.
So should it be routinely given to
malnourished cancer patients?
The answer is not as
obvious as one might think.
When it was put to the test
in dozens of randomized trials,
the results were both
disappointing and surprising.
Parenteral nutrition didn't just
fail to provide any benefit
to these patients;
it caused harm.
Not only did it appear to
provide zero survival benefit,
there was an increase in
complications and infections,
and a decrease in tumor
response to chemotherapy,
presumed to be due to all
those extra nutrients
stimulating tumor growth.
Similarly, oral nutritional
interventions in malnourished
patients with cancer,
like giving them bottles of Ensure,
found no survival advantage.
Despite the lack of demonstrated
benefit, the knee jerk reaction
of many oncologists to the idea
of cancer patients fasting
is the concern they're not
eating enough already.
But you don't know
until you put it to the test,
which we'll explore next.